Guide to the Collection on Enslavement in Cuba MSS.569
Fales Library and Special Collections
Collection on Enslavement in Cuba
1809-1898
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fales Library
MSS.569
2 linear foot in 2 flat boxes
The time period covered by this collection was the final century of 400 years of Spanish colonization of the island of Cuba. Although Spain and Great Britain agreed to end the trade of enslaved people in Spanish colonies by 1820, an estimated one million enslaved Africans were brought to Cuba by Spanish colonists. Cuba formally ended its participation in the Transatlantic Slave Trade in 1867, and abolished the legal enslavement of people in 1886. Enslaved people endured family separation, harsh manual labor on sugar plantations and in sugar mills, and labor within an enslaver's household. Enslaved women were often victims of sexual assault and exploitation. From 1847-1874, hundreds of thousands of Chinese men were trafficked to Cuba as indentured laborers by the Spanish, French, British, and Americans. The group of Chinese indentured workers, later known as "coolies," were subjected to conditions analog to slavery. This collection consists of documents concerning slavery in Spanish-colonized Cuba between 1809 and 1898, and the infrastructure that supported Spanish and American plantation owners at the expense of enslaved and indentured individuals. Materials include telegrams, contracts, identification papers, travel licenses, birth notices, marriage and baptism records, death and burial certificates, purchase and insurance documents, and manumission records documenting various aspects of enslavement in Cuba, including the economics of the Transatlantic Slave Trade, demographics of Cuban populations, England's abolition of slavery, the transportation of indentured Chinese laborers to Cuba, family relationships in the context of slavery, living and working conditions on sugar cane plantations, and manumission processes.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of documents concerning slavery in Spanish-colonized Cuba between 1809 and 1898 and the infrastructure that supported Spanish and American plantation owners at the expense of enslaved and indentured individuals. Materials include telegrams, contracts, identification papers, travel licenses, birth notices, marriage and baptism records, death and burial certificates, purchase and insurance documents, and manumission records documenting various aspects of enslavement in Cuba, including the economics of the Transatlantic Slave Trade, demographics of Cuban populations, England's abolition of slavery, the transportation of indentured Chinese laborers to Cuba, family relationships in the context of slavery, living and working conditions on sugar cane plantations, and manumission processes.
Spanish transcriptions of selected documents are available by request to Special Collections staff.
Glossary of frequently used terms throughout the collection:
Bozal: A juridical as well as colloquial term used to designate a person who either was recently trafficked from Africa and therefore had not learned the colonial language and customs, or someone who, despite having arrived earlier, had still not given up their own language and traditions, often perceived as not speaking the colony's proper language.
Carabalí: Also known as Kalabari, or Karabali. People from the Bight of Biafra, parts of present-day eastern Nigeria, Cameroon, Equatorial Guinea, and northern Gabon.
Cimarrón: Maroon. A person who was enslaved but has run away.
Colono: Term used to refer to the Chinese indentured workers in their contracts, literally translating to colonist or settler.
Congo: A person from West Central Africa.
Criollo: Born in the colony, in this case, Cuba.
Ganga: Most probably derived from Kanga. Used for people from Sierra Leone.
Lucumí: Yoruba person from present-day Nigeria, Benin, and Togo.
Makua: Also referred to as Wamakua; also written Macua. Bantu-speaking people from northern Mozambique and the southern Tanzania border.
Mandinga: Also written Mandinka. Person from Senegambia.
Moreno: Dark-skinned. Used to refer to Black people.
Pardo: Used to refer to mixed people of Spanish and African origin.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were purchased from bookseller Kevin Jackson by Timothy V. Johnson, NYU Librarian for Africana Studies, Anthropology and Food Studies in December 2014; original provenance is unknown. The collection was transferred to the Fales Library and Special Collections in 2017. The accession number associated with this purchase is 2019.010.
Separated Materials
Folder 1 in the inventory contained a grouping of 80 documents related to the case of five enslaved people at a sugar mill in Rio Nuevo who killed a man they believed to be the Governor General of Cuba on July 8, 1842. This item was removed from the collection and cataloged separately as HV6535.C9 C66 1842.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the seller.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Iron gall ink present in many documents in the collection has caused paper loss. Some documents are partially legible as a result.
Historical Note
The time period covered by this collection was the final century of 400 years of Spanish colonization of the island of Cuba. Although Spain and Great Britain agreed to end the trade of enslaved people in Spanish colonies by 1820, an estimated one million enslaved Africans were brought to Cuba by Spanish colonists. Cuba formally ended its participation in the Transatlantic Slave Trade in 1867, and abolished the legal enslavement of people in 1886. Enslaved people endured family separation, harsh manual labor on sugar plantations and in sugar mills, and labor within an enslaver's household. Enslaved women were often victims of sexual assault and exploitation.
From 1847-1874, hundreds of thousands of Chinese men were trafficked to Cuba as indentured laborers by the Spanish, French, British, and Americans. The group of Chinese indentured workers, later known as "coolies", were subjected to conditions analog to slavery. In port cities like Hong Kong and Macao, Chinese men were kidnapped or coerced into signing contracts by enslavers posing as recruitment agents. Although the contracts offered freedom after eight years, this freedom was not enforced, and the laborers often died before the term ended due to malnourishment and abusive conditions.
Slave trade -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Economic aspects -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Social aspects -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Foreign workers, Chinese -- Cuba.; Chinese -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Vital statistics records; Free papers; Enslaved Persons; Spain -- Colonies; Forced labor -- Cuba
- Cuban Manuscript Concerning the Incarceration of Self-Liberated Cimarrones, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Letter sent by Matías Gallegos to the King, reporting on a previous communication in which Gallegos details the specific characteristics of the cimarrones held in Villa Clara, in accordance with the King's instructions.
  A transcription of this document is available by request.
- Cuban Telegram Regarding Human Trafficking and Slavery, 1857-08-20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This telegram regarding human trafficking and slavery was sent to the General Captain of Cuba, by the Governor of Cardenas, Luis Andriani. Andriani reports the disappearance of bozales who were aboard a ship in Cayo Bahia de Cadiz during the 15th and 16th days of the same month.
- Death Certificate for Estanislao, an Enslaved Chinese Man, 1872-02-18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  According to the death certificate, Estanislao, whose ethnicity here is stated as "asiatico" (Asian), died at Charity Hospital in the city of San Felipe y Santiago. According to the document, he was to be buried in the General Cemetery of the city.
- Insurance Certificate for a Person Enslaved by Joaquin Soler, 1860-03-01 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This certificate, created by La Protectora Compañia General Cubana de Seguros Mutuos Sobre la Vida de Esclavos, includes information such as the price of the insurance, the corresponding legal articles, and the signature of the insurance director. It does not appear to include the name of the enslaved person.
- Two Letters Addressing the Burial of Fetuses, 1866-08-07 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  These letters were issued by the Church of the Holy Spirit and the Church of Monserrate in Havana. They are addressed to the Secretary of the Bishopric and explain the burial and certification of deceased fetuses who could not receive the sacrament of baptism. The first letter mentions a specific case involving the abortion of a Black woman, Doña N.N., "also known as la Morena or Parda." The full name of the woman, and the name of the deceased are not provided.
  Transcriptions of these documents are available by request.
- Document Summarizing Enslaved Peoples Expenditures, 1818-1819 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  The expenses include food, housing and the preparation of the terrain (hollar). The document is signed by Juan de Sosa y Albarado.
- La Providencia Insurance Document for an Enslaved Person in Havana, 1859-09-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  The document is an agreement between José Pardú and La Providencia Company.
- Document Attesting the Baptism of Maria del Rosario, 1816-12-11-1816-12-12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  This document serves as a confirmation of the baptism of Maria del Rosario, a Black woman enslaved by Juan Garcia de Casares, in order for her to marry another enslaved person.
- Notice on the Escape and Apprehension of a Man in Charge of Transporting Cadavers, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Letter signed by Alexandro Ramirez sent to the bishop of Havana informing of the disobedience, escape, and capture of an enslaved man in charge of transporting cadavers to their burial places.
- Identity Paper [Cédula] for Dominga, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Dominga was a 21 year old woman enslaved by Juan Ruiz. This cédula contains twelve articles pertaining to the agreement of the holding of enslaved people.
- Identity Paper for Gerónimo Ganga, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  The document contains the Decree of December 19th, 1854, issued by the Civil Superior Government of the Island (Decreto de 19 de diciembre de 1854 del Gobierno Superior Civil de la Isla), as well as the Decree of September 1st, 1857. These decrees outline the conditions for holding, trading, and transporting enslaved persons. This specific document serves to identify 59-year-old Gerónimo, of Ganga origin (now known as Sierra Leone), who was enslaved by Juan Azpeitia.
- Manumission Document for Lelicia Frerejo, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Lelicia (possible mispelling for "Leticia" or "Felicia") Frerejo was enslaved at the Ingenio (plantation) of Baracoa.
- Burial Document of an Enslaved Person, 1879-08-25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  According to this document, it was the duty of the patrons (patronos) to cover the burial expenses of their enslaved individuals. Juan S. Aguirre is being required to comply with this obligation after previously refusing to pay. The document does not state the name or number of the deceased.
- Baptism Document for Francisco Herrera, 1842-07-06-1842-07-08 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  The document, issued in Matanzas, constitutes a petition for proof of baptism of Francisco Herrera, who was between 25 and 28 years old at the time, enslaved by Pedro Herrera.
- Judicial Trial of Rosa Delgado and Maria de la Luz Delgado for Having Buried an Infant on Unholy Ground, 1849-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  This document follows the denunciation made by the Lieutenant Priest of San Jose de las Lajas in which he claimed the two women, both enslaved, engaged in an illicit burial of the child of Maria de la Luz Delgado. Other free Black women testified on their behalf and the case was resolved in favor of the women.
- La Protectora Insurance Receipt for an Enslaved Person, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Insurance receipt issued in Havana by the Director General to Francisco Equileos regarding the purchase of an enslaved person.
- Telegram Concerning the Persecution of Trading Enslaved People by the Lieutenant Governor of Cuba, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Telegram sent by the Lieutenant Governor of San Cristobal, Francisco Fernandes de la Reguera, informing the Governor of Havana he will conduct an inspection of the coasts of the locality of San Diego.
- Judicial Deposit of Enslaved People, 1851-10-30 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  The document states that Nicolás "Criollito," who was enslaved by Marcos Albares, was handed over to Carlos Criado as a result of a dispute. The word "Criollito" possibly refers to Nicolás as being criollo.
- La Protectora Insurance Receipt for an Enslaved Person, 1859-05-18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  This insurance, corresponding to a 1% fee of the total capital reported by the enslavers, was established on May 9th of the same year as a precaution against any incidents that might occur throughout the year. The document is signed on behalf of the slaveholders Martínez y Barrera.
- Stamped Document for Renting Out Two Enslaved Persons, 1872-02-20 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  The document was issued in Matanzas. The family who rented the enslaved individuals had the last name Arzauregui Gonsales. The receipt does not state the names of the enslaved, who were in the service of the other party for twenty days.
- Legal Agreement Regarding Deposit of Francisco Carabalí, 1847-05-04 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  The legal agreement states that power over Francisco's life is being transferred from Juana Franchi de Alfaro, the widow of Francisco Franchi de Alfaro, to the Fourth Mayor, for him to exercise at his discretion.
- La Providencia Receipt for a Fee Paid for Incidents Associated with the Holding of Enslaved People, 1856-04-15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Receipt for fee paid to La Providencia insurance by enslaver Francisco Alonso. The fee is said to cover incidents that occurred from January until March 31 of the same year.
- Identification Paper for Guillermo Ceta, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Government identification paper permitting the travel of Guillermo Ceta, a man enslaved by Cristobal Alonso of La Habana, to Pueblo.
- Memo on the Presence of Enslaved African People in Cienfuegos, 1864-03-12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Short note inquiring about the presence of newly arrived enslaved African people (bozales) in the vicinities of Cienfuegos, specifically in Yaguaramas and Cartagena. Sent from Habana.
- Proof of Bachelorhood and Christianity of Enslaved Manuel Maria Clavel in Order for Him to Marry Maria Luisa, Also Enslaved, 1809-04-08 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  These series of documents issued in Santo Domingo serve as proof of the single status and christianity of Manuel Maria Clavel, as well as his lack of blood kinship with Maria Luisa. Both individuals were enslaved by the colonel Martin Ugarte. Two freed individuals and one enslaved person testify in favor of Clavel, stating they had known him since their youth in Santo Domingo.
- Telegram to the General Captain of Havana from Francisco F. de la Regera, 1864-09-21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Telegram sent to the General Captain in Habana from Francisco F. de la Regera concerning the contraband of enslaved Africans (bozales) in San Diego.
- Proof of Baptism of the Enslaved Person Rafael, Lucumi, in Order for Him to Marry a Woman Enslaved by the Same Individual, 1816-12-20 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  This document serves as proof of the baptism and christianity of Rafael, of African Lucumi origin, enslaved by Agustin Lopes in San Juan de Jaruco, in order for him to marry another woman enslaved by the same man; her name, although not entirely clear, appears once and is shortened as Sūa.
  A transcription of this document is avaialble by request.
- La Providencia Receipt for Insurance of Enslaved People, 1860-01-01 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Receipt for the "medio por ciento" fee paid by enslaver Ambrosio Maria Rendon to La Providencia insurance.
- Marriage Contract between Two Emancipated People, 1817-08-17 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Marriage contract between Francisco Andrade, of possible Nigerian origin (stated here as "de nación caravali,") and Marcelina Ximenes, both free people.
- Telegram Concerning Surveilling of Punta de Cartas Sent by Ramon Menduiña, 1865-09-30 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Ramon Menduiña, lieutenant governor of Pinar del Río, informed the governor of Havana he was leaving La Coloma in direction of Punta de Cartas in order to surveil the coast.
  Biographical / Historical
  Born in Salamanca, Spain, in 1815, Ramón Menduiña López was a field marshal and knight of the order of San Fernando who died in 1890 in Madrid. After having participated in many battles throughout the Spanish kingdom, he was sent to Mexico, where he served under General Prim. When that campaign ended, he remained under the authority of the Captain General of Cuba, who appointed him military commander of Bayamo in August 1862. After being promoted to colonel in March 1864, he assumed command of the Disciplined Militias Regiment based in Güines. In September 1865, he was appointed military commander of Pinar del Río. He became commander of Bayamo, where he exercised control until 1879 when he was declared commander-in-chief of Port-au-Prince (Haiti). He returned to Spain in 1883, where he remained until his death.
- Documents Regarding the Death and Burial of Felix, 1854-07-17-1854-08-07 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Felix, a Black criollo man, enslaved by Juan Delgado, drowned in a well in June 12, 1854, in Bainoa. Felix was 30 years old. These documents refer to the processing of the death certificate and burial permit.
- Correspondence regarding the grave of Felix, 1854-06-12 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  June 12, 1854. Felix, a Black criollo man enslaved by Juan Delgado, drowned in a well in 1854. Felix was 30 years old. In these letters, Juan Serafin Delgado, son of Juan Delgado, and Antonio Martin ask the priest of Bainoa for his permission to bury Felix in the local cemetery. Delgado's letter also states that Felix's death was "casual" ("muerto de una muerte casual").
- Document Referencing the Emancipation of Blas, 1842-10-19 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  The document, signed by Francisco Rodriguez and addressed to the archbishop of Guatemala (Cuba), constitutes a petition to include in the baptismal record Blas (of unknown surname) his manumission from the plantation Manuelita and the enslaver María de Jesús García.
- Petition of Marriage for José Ramón and Maria Anta Gonzalez, Both Enslaved, 1815-11-06 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  In the town of Regla, Federico Pau gives his consent for José Ramón, of Mandinga origin and enslaved by him, to marry Maria Anta (possibly Antonia) Gonzales, who was enslaved by Santiago Espinola.
- Certificate of Indenture for Chinese Laborer Anselmo, 1863-05-04 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  This document states that Anselmo, a 23-year-old laborer from China, was contracted to work in a quarry for eight years and for Carmen Herrera for an equal amount of time. The document also includes articles 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and 11 of the decree of June 5, 1855.
- Contract Enslaving Francisco Real, 1852-09-02 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  La Comision de Poblacion Blanca one-year contract regarding Francisco Real, a 20 year old man from Palma, Canarias, who was indentured by Aur [possibly Aureliano] r Suares de la Rosa. The contract also specifies that Francisco would work in the fields and the payment and conditions to which he was subjected.
- Contract Enslaving Justo Asivea, 1868-06 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Tenencia de Gobierno de Guanajay one-year contract regarding Justo Asivea, a 28 year old Chinese man who was enslaved by Andres Fin. The contract specifies the type of job in the fields, the payment, and conditions to which Justo was subjected.
- Contract Enslaving Emeterio Sau Achin, 1868-05-29 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Tenencia de Gobierno de Guanajay contract regarding Emeterio Sau Achin, a 28 year old Chinese man from Canton formerly enslaved by Manuel Martinez and enslaved by Paulino Ligarreta per this contract.
- Document of the Death and Burial of Domingo, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  According to the document, Domingo was an enslaved Chinese man.
- Contract for Julian Aguat, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Gobierno Politico de la Habana contract regarding Julian Aguat, a 28 year old Chinese man from Macao who was an indentured laborer for Manuel Dorado.
- Identification Document for Leopoldo, 1863-03-03 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Gobierno Politico de la Habana identification document regarding Leopoldo, an indentured 24 year old Chinese man from "Sunhen" who worked for M.B. Pereda for a period of eight years at a quarry. The document states Leopoldo is now under contract with Mayoral and Buquis, residents ("hacendados y vecinos") of El Calvario.
- Contract Enslaving Nine Spanish People, 1854-01-31 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Real Junta de Fomento de la Isla de Cuba contract regarding nine Spanish people who were indentured by Gaspar Hernandez: Jose Hernandez; his wife Bernarda Rodriguez; their sons and daughters Nareisa, Antonio, Maria, and Gregorio; Novento Luis Garcia; Antonio Calaturio; and Silvestre Juan Rodriguez. The documents ends with a note stating that, while most of the listed people are under 12-month contracts, some are only going to serve for eight months, and that the cost of food for the women is lowered in accordance to the agreement of the board of October 26.
- Document Regarding Enslaved People Who Escaped from a Ship, 1842-08 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Biographical Note
  Gerónimo Valdés (1784–1855) was a Spanish military figure and administrator. Born in Villarín, in Asturias, he participated in the battle of Ayacucho (1824), which was a defeat for the Spanish. He served as Viceroy of Navarre from 1833 to 1834 and also served as Minister of War. He fought on the Liberal (Isabeline) side in the First Carlist War. Valdés lost the Battle of Artaza (April 22, 1835). Valdés signed the Lord Eliot Convention soon after, regulating the treatment of prisoners during that war. He later served as captain-general of Valencia, and of Galicia, and served as governor of Cuba from 1841 to September 1843.
  This printed memo was issued by the Captain General of Cuba, Gerónimo Valdés. It accounts that, according to British deputies, there was an illegal disembarkation of escaped enslaved people who hid in a farm near Matanzas. Valdés also states that, in agreement with the dictum of the general counsel, farms should not be registered.
- Documentation Regarding Sale of the La Constancia Sugar Mill and List of 72 Enslaved People, 1856-02-12 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  List of people enslaved at the plantation la Costancia: Bernardo of Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); Fernando; José Maria; Domingo of Lucumi; José Maria; Antonio; Ysidro; Ramon; Miguel; Alejandro; Nicolas; Juan Bautista; Pablo; Martin; José de la Luz; Julian; Pascual; José de Jesus; Juaquin of Abcinia (possibly Abisinia, now known as Ethiopia); Manuel; Carmelo of Macua; Gerbasio; Facundo; Rafael of Congo; Domingo; Antonio Peña; Remigio, criollo; Luis; Cristobal; Roque; Eusebio; José del Rosario; Juan; Simon, criollo; Abraham; Lorenzo; Juaquin; Candelario; Salustiano; Miguel; Juan de Mata; Eugenio; Fernando; Gregorio; Antonio; Hilario; Regino; Carlos; Juliana of Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); Josefa; Antonia; Paula; Matilde; Maria de Jesus of Congo; Victoria of Abcinia; Asuncion; Catalina; Vicenta of Carabali; Basilia, criolla; Barbara; Ynés; Petrona; Asuncion; Ana Maria; Luisa; Eulogia; Marcelina, criolla; Zacarias; Ynes, Rosa, Florentina, criolla, Olaya.